uh today is part two of our session with
uh
kent summers uh ken summers founded and
successfully exited three startups over
a 16-year period
kent teaches the b2b sales for startups
iap course
at mit and is a visiting lecturer at hbs
kent is an executive leadership coach in
the harvard advanced
leadership initiative is on the teaching
faculty of thai boston
and the mastering sales program at
northwestern's kellogg school
and he serves on the boards of sigma
labs a nasdaq company
uh as well as mass materials tech and
iq3 connect thank you everyone for
joining us on the great feedback
that we got from last session and hand
it over
to kent hello everyone
i'm glad to be back with you we covered
a lot of ground in a short period of
time
last tuesday um today is going to be the
same deal
i'm going to try to cover as much ground
as i can
an hour with you so you you walk away
with something that's
that's helpful last session
we focused on sales tools and mechanics
the profile working the pipeline the
different stages
of sales and do's and don'ts
and best practices for
working a pipeline um
this afternoon i'm going to shift uh the
discussion a little bit
um i want to cover um
a couple topics uh that are usually
uh challenging to a lot of early stage
companies
sales forecasting and understanding your
sales
economics and then what i want to do is
follow up or wrap up with offering you
some effective methods uh to help
prospects
uh opt in or opt out of your
sales process as you may recall on
tuesday we talked about the different
types of
sales people's attitudes and behavior
where
the most matured uh sales
skills is what's called a sales
facilitator so i want to share some of
those
sales facilitator skills
with you this afternoon and hopefully if
there's some
time at the end here i've got a heart
stop at
2 10 we can make some room for some q a
if you have other questions just pop
them to joe via chat
you can interrupt me as we go through
so i learned sales i never went to
business school
um i learned sales through failure um
many many years of failure so i like to
i like to offer sales techniques in the
context of a failed
case mini case study here so
with that i'm going to start out today's
session with a sales fail
here and explain to you why it failed
all right so you're the founder
uh of a two-year-old dc back startup
your product sells for a fixed price of
50k
you've been actively selling now for
nine 12 months building your pipeline so
far
you know congratulations you landed
three customers so you've taken in
you've booked 150k in revenue
um you've got five well-qualified
opportunities in your pipeline
they look exactly like the three that
you just closed
you're not so much you're not so sure
about timing
um but they're very well qualified
opportunities
and you have a board meeting with your
investors next week to assess your
financing needs
and they sent you a note
and they want as part of this meeting
they want to understand the value of
your pipeline
and how much money do you expect to
close this month in this quarter
now these are very typical questions
of an investor especially when you're
being drip fed
by investors at the early stage
so you have to you have to figure out a
way to
answer these very important questions
um i can tell you this that
all of us have a difficulty making uh
predictions
here it's always a very hard and
challenging
uh thing to do here and it turns out
that there's quite a few methods
available for people to forecast sales
um a lot of them are in inexact
uh for one reason or another there's not
just one method out there that's
reliable
um a couple of the popular methods out
there
you've got the the optimist
you know they feel very very good
about their confidence in closing
business and they take
optimistic view of their business and
their pipeline
i can share with you personally that is
a founder
optimism has never served me well as a
founder
and of course the uh flip side of that
is uh sandy the sandbagger
you know somebody that is pretty good at
managing people's expectations and
living leaving him or her the
opportunity to outperform those
those expectations those are several
popular methods what i like to do is
offer you
a method that i've developed and used in
the past for myself
and for lots of companies that i work
with that tends to
work very well because it's not only
reliable
it's very simple so it's called the
weighted pipeline
and this is a way of measuring the
relative value of your pipeline
versus the absolute value
so let's take the example of that 50k
fixed
offering here in the context of
the different stages of my sales process
i would ascribe a 25
likelihood of close if i'm at the buyer
interest
stage versus a 40
likelihood of close if the timing is
known
and i've established uh i've built a
business case in the buyer interest and
60 and so on um
so basically all you do is you multiply
these weightings
times the value of the offering and that
gives you the weighted value
so it's very very simple so my question
is
where do these waiting percentages come
from are these things that you just made
up
or so forth uh if you can just um
uh chat where you think these um
these weightings come came from and i'll
give you a clue i covered them in
tuesday's
uh session does anybody have an idea
where
these waiting percentages come from you
just make them up
or anybody have any thoughts on that
bingo such you the conversion rate
bingo so it does come from the sales
funnel but it is the conversion rate in
the sales funnel that's exactly right
these are the conversions percentages
between the different stages of your
sale
so you can see here i'm not sure where
this um markup is coming from
that's interesting um
it's not me can you see the markup joe
yeah i can i can i can see it i must be
one of the participants
oh okay well i appreciate the
contribution there you should hold off
on that
um yeah so you can see there's a big
difference here between 150 k
in relative value versus 250k
and absolute value that's the main
concept here
so the sales stages you know um
arrive at milestones in your sales
process that are practical for you
you know i offered you uh what i
consider to be fairly generic
recommendations on tuesday suspects
prospects opportunities you know the
whole difference between leads
and that how they sort of narrow down in
those conversion metrics
uh think through your stages arrive at
sales stages and milestones that are
practical for you
um and the conversion metrics themselves
you have to be patient it's going to be
a year or more
before they really help you inform your
sales forecasts
they will never help their a very
reliable method
for sales forecasting and they will
never help you if you don't
start capturing your conversion metrics
uh today right they're not going to help
you today though
you just have to collect the data
they're going to help you debug your
sales process
they have to increase from left to right
and they're going to help you
they're going to become really valuable
to inform your sales forecast later on
so get in the practice of capturing
those conversion methods
so i want to go through the same
weighted
pipeline example in a variable priced
offering
against a calendar so you can answer the
question
about you know cash flows so again
same thing here same stages same
weightings
and the variable the potential value of
the deal is variable depending upon
other factors the size of your offering
the size of the company whatever your
revenue model is
in this case i'm capturing the potential
value of the deal
what stage they're at in my sales
process in the timing
if it's known and just with this
information
i'm able to not only come up with the
weighted value the relative value
but i'm able to determine when that's
likely to close
over the next uh four quarters
the reason i don't have any money
going uh is
uh prospective booking over the next
four quarters for company f
is i am unaware of their timing right so
if you don't know something
don't put it in your forecast i would
also recommend
um sometimes when you attempt to
forecast revenue
um and it depends upon the length of
your sales cycle of course but for
most longer term b2b sales cycles
ie 8 9 10 month cycles
i think you'll be better served to
forecast your revenues quarter to
quarter versus month to month
because otherwise you'll find you're
investing a lot of time
constantly pushing your forecast back
month by month by month and quarter just
seems to be a little bit
more stable so there's a big difference
between the absolute value
and the relative value again here
in the variable price offering so
a sales forecast is nothing more than
the deal value
factored by the stage of your sales
process over the calendar
it's that simple i would argue that
if you get much more complex than this
then you're going to get into
diminishing returns on the value
and how helpful a forecasting model
actually is
all right sales economics um
i think i shared this with you on
tuesday that sales is your most
expensive investment in terms of real
and in terms of opportunity costs
and we all know that you can't manage
what you don't measure
so when it comes to sales the term of
the day
is coca or cost of customer acquisition
uh when you when you subtract your cost
of cup
customer acquisition from your bookings
then you have your go to market margins
right what's it cost what money is left
over
after your fully burdened sales and
marketing
investment right to apply
to invest in different areas of your
company
so your coca is what matters
um the deeper a prospect
this is an important concept the deeper
a prospect gets into your sales process
by definition the more expensive they
become so you need to know your coca
at each stage of the sales process
to id areas where you can improve
it's also very helpful
to identify areas where you can scale
in other words where you have a low uh
cost
uh that tends to be very scalable the
reverse is also
um not true uh you won't be able to
scale things with a high cost of scales
so what i'm going to do is i'm going to
walk you through a small
case study here of a software
development
services company that generates their
leads 100
from seo and ppc with uh three
full-time sales reps right
so and forgive me on this slide i'm
about to break um
every powerpoint rule known to man on
this one i'm gonna cram a lot of
information
on here but hopefully it helps you
understand sort of the larger picture
here so like any good company we got a
couple of websites up here not one
so that we can do proper a to b testing
on lead generation here which is
important when you're
relying 100 on seo and ppc
and i'm investing roughly 215 000
a year in um in google
ad campaigns and co-marketing uh
campaigns
and as a result i'm generating
over 100 000 visitors a year to my
websites
split between the two sites uh website a
and website b
within the website uh we offer
uh people uh lots of different ways that
they can contact us either through a
request for information
form a live chat for phone calls
and from this uh the investment of
uh 215 000 in those campaigns
yielded 500 inbound inquiries or roughly
two a day
they are prospects we haven't talked
with them yet
um of course in addition to
taking on new business we we don't know
who these customers are so we reach out
to them
and we talk to them and one out of 10
of those prospects converts to an
opportunity
so out of the 10 inbound inquiries we
received
uh applying our own
company profile and buyer profile
criteria
we determined that one in 10 of those
prospects were actually qualified to
take our time they were good qualified
opportunities now addition to those
opportunities we've already got
existing clients and we're busy farming
and growing those accounts
so between the hunting and the farming
we have a total of 81 opportunities that
were working
across the sales team from those 81
opportunities
75 proposals went out the door
resulting in just under 50
signed agreements 22 with
new clients and 27 from
his existing clients and a couple of
duds people that signed an agreement but
just went away which happens
uh the the yield uh for this in terms of
bookings was just under four million
dollars
split roughly 50 50 between the current
annual period and the forward-looking
12-month period
when you look at the conversion rates
between these different stages when you
go from suspect to prospect
it's minutia is what you might expect
but it's that 10 that went from
prospects to opportunities
and increased again significantly
to 60 percent between opportunities
to customers signed customers we have a
large number
uh on the conversion rate because we
have a small number
in uh the folks that we let through our
process and
take up our time so in other words we're
very selective
in the folks that we let into our sales
process
so four and a half percent of those 500
inquiries closed as new business
which uh by comparison is is pretty good
um and of course a much higher
percentage
uh closed in farming simply because
the confidence and the trust was already
established
it was a logical next step in a project
and we're already in their accounts
payable system
so it was a lot easier to convert those
it was new
new customers onboarding now let's look
at the coca let's look at the cost of
customer acquisition
at each stage each time somebody landed
on our website it cost us
1.75 each time somebody reached out to
us the cost
for that prospect was 430 dollars
which is the 500 divided by
the our our total spend divided by 500.
when they reach the opportunity phase we
now have invested
four thousand two hundred dollars uh in
each opportunity that we're actively
working and they're not a customer yet
and by the time those few that do
convert to a customer
they cost us just under ten thousand so
ten thousand just under ten thousand
is our cost of customer acquisition
for for a client
so let's look at this in terms of the
this the
just the sales economics the numbers
from a total bookings of
three million nine our marketing spent
on google adword and remarketing
campaigns was two hundred and fifteen
thousand dollars
the sales reps cost us ninety k each
with an eight percent commission on the
one million annual quota
so that's a total base of 360 k
and total commissions on performance at
quota of 312
for a total sales spend of 672 thousand
combined with the total marketing spend
a sales and marketing spend of eight
hundred and eighty seven thousand
dollars
divide three million nine to eight
eighty seven
our cost of customer acquisition is 23
in other words for every dollar this
company
invests in sales and marketing yields
three dollars in cash flow
let's talk about some things worth
measuring
the source the cost and the conversion
from prospecting uh from from lead
to uh prospecting right your leads which
ones are working
which ones are not working what do they
cost you
the conversions between prospect
opportunity and customers
and the coca right this
is valuable to measure between new and
existing customers
it's valuable to measure by individual
sales rep
so you can get some sense of what the
expected level of performance is and
if you offer different products also
valuable to measure at the product level
and you can even you know put this in
pivot tables and look at sales rep by
individual project by new and existing
customers
right that's kind of the matrix that you
want to measure here
right but it's really any metric that's
unique to your go-to-market model that
helps you measure sales efficiency
performance and margin
so the the bottom line here is
your ability to measure money in and
money out
at a detailed level and on a consistent
basis
is the number one skill for startups
that survive it's also the number one
skills that investor looks for
if you can go to an investor and say
listen for every dollar
we put in go to market yields
three dollars in free cash flow you're
going to have investors
lined up with their checkbooks
all right let's jump into another failed
case study that's it for
uh sales forecasting and sales economics
what i want to do now is um shift um the
discussion
to sales facilitator methods that help
you opt in or opt out prospects in your
sales process
all right uh so another mini case study
here
you get a phone call from the clo with a
large pharma
company uh she recommended uh she heard
um of your company through one of her
colleagues you have a nice
45 minute chat on the phone and as a
result of that
you both agree um to meet in person
she said she's very busy i've got about
an hour of my time
and uh you wanted to make best use of
this this is a very large company
it's right in your sweet spot of your
company profile
so you come very very well prepared
you're loaded for bear
when you show up you've got information
on your company
you've got your demo ready you've got
your roi calculator your competitive
matrix
uh your implementation method
you even leave behind two case studies
and
you know great customer references you
you know you didn't leave
any stone on unturned
the one hour meeting turns into three
hours it was the best sales meeting you
ever had
and that's because you were so super
well prepared and you covered all the
bases
there wasn't anything you were
unprepared uh in response to
the questions or requests that came from
the prospective customer
you're pretty excited about it um
but for some reason three weeks have now
passed
um and despite numerous emails and phone
calls
um you're you're getting ghosted the c
the clo has gone completely radio
silent why did this prospect
go from totally interested to totally
unresponsive and this is one of the big
lessons that i learned in sales because
you know when you get somebody's
attention and they're a great fit
for what you do and they start asking a
bunch of questions
all you want to do is just feed them
everything that they need
to move the opportunity forward and to
help position your company
and earn their business
and you're not very disciplined about
that and what i learned
was that i covered all my bases that was
the problem
that was not an asset in this meeting
that was a problem
in sales parlance i call this spilling
all your candy in the lobby
right have the discipline not to provide
not to attempt to go from zero to close
in a single meeting and cover all your
bases what's going on
here is the co the reason she's not
contacting you
is she feels that she has everything she
needs from you she doesn't need any
additional information and likely she's
using all that great information that
you provided her as a baseline to
compare you to others out there in the
market
she doesn't have a reason to contact you
any further
so the lesson here is that customers
are built through trust and confidence
that's established through
a back and forth collaborative process
not by unloading all your information in
the first meeting
so let's talk about those sales
prospecting do's and don'ts
the occam raiser principle applies here
less
material is more almost every one of
your topics
gets on a single page right you can
always make details available
wait for people to ask for them don't
provide the detail
up front it's likely to be confusing
right share your material with people
throughout the sales discussion piece by
piece as appropriate as requested or
needed
to support the sales process don't just
dump it
on people and use this
metering out of the material as a means
to pay attention
to telltale signs of buying or stalling
is the prospect are they easy to get a
hold of are they willing to trade you
insights in exchange for the information
you're providing them
what about the cadence and the momentum
of the discussion
all right um when you dump all your
information on somebody you have no
way of measuring their interest or
cadence in fact there is no cadence
it's all done so if i can
offer you a recipe for sales failure
it's having a meeting with somebody
giving them a bunch of information
scheduling another meeting
giving them the rest of your information
and asking them for business
and what you're going to get is a big
question
to the contrary the recipe for sales
success
is have a very focused meeting
for example your initial meeting might
be on a needs assessment
and where you determine fit and you
provide them a background on your
company and you
schedule another meeting and uh you pro
they requested how you stack up against
other things they're considering
so you give them the deck and the
competitive matrix
and in exchange uh they give you some
insight on how um
your solution is going to be valued
inside their organization
in other words the economic impact of
your solution
similarly you schedule another meeting
where you go into the demo you share
some white papers and in exchange they
provide you some insights
on how large of an impact uh
how much of the organization is impacted
by this not just the value
and so on and so forth right
so instead of one meeting or two meeting
what i've done is i've stretched it out
and i've
i've built i've i've left some room for
building
the relationship and i've had very very
focused discussions
and because of that i was able to
request
a very focused information insights in
exchange when you follow this process
the do together just becomes the logical
next step
of your discussion it's not an ask it's
okay
this all looks good let's you know let's
do this
so try to build a sales process where
uh you build intelligence and insights
uh with the customer and in exchange
they gain knowledge and trust and
confidence in you
and your team if it turns out that
you're marching somebody down
this process and uh they stop responding
to you uh at say the third meeting
well guess what they're not qualified to
take your time
um you might want to understand why but
nonetheless they're not moving forward
and you just saved yourself a bunch of
time
of uh additional meetings when they're
not qualified
if they're unwilling to trade with you
they don't trust you they're not
qualified right
a good buy or seller relationship
is the exchange of value in both
directions
not just one direction
and if people are asking you for
customer references throughout this
entire process
you do not provide them
and the reason is i like to use customer
references
is the very last step in my sales
process
when they're looking at one of my
proposals and where the customer
references are much more impactful
you'll find that people will insist or
ask
for them early my pat response is
hey listen my customers are very busy
um and if it turns out that at some
point
in the future you're serious about doing
business with us in other words you know
you're evaluating a proposal we will be
more than happy to share references
with you but until that point i really
want to protect
my clients from a lot of prospects
of prospective customers taking up their
valuable time i hope you appreciate that
that's
how we will treat you if you become one
of our clients
when you explain it like that 98 percent
of the time people
will respect that and back off
so exercise sales discipline prospects
because they have their own agenda will
often
take shortcuts in sales you just simply
do not have that luxury do not let
prospects dictate your behavior
this doesn't sound very intuitive um but
it's actually one of the things i'm
hopeful that you walk
away from uh over these last two
sessions
is the concept that by
um segmenting and slowing down
your sales process you will actually
speed up sales
it sounds counterintuitive but it's true
and you do this by sharing your tools
and your value wisely
and using them to gauge the level of
interest
in whether a prospect is a good use of
your time you can never
do that if you don't keep your powder
dry right you really have to
meet the value out over a longer period
of time
and give yourself room to build a
relationship
where doing business is just the logical
next step
in a sales conversation
prospective customers value lots of
things right
capabilities and implementation support
underlying science technology the
business case whatever
team sales is your opportunity to show
the breadth of your team
the individual strengths of people on
your team
and actually how you work and how you
coordinate as a team
so team sales is your opportunity as a
founder
to work smarter not harder
so let me give you a recipe for
repeatable
sales success with the facilitator here
right you have these various meetings
right
the operational buyer compliance
technical financial buyer
and you align those conversations with
the subject the
appropriate subject matter experts on
your team operational buyer connecting
with your pm
compliance with your legal technical
with your cto financial with your cfo
right that's your job in sales is to
align those conversations
right and offering people off ramps
right any one of these people can veto
your deal based upon their own
perspective here so the facilitator
is proactively offering people the
opportunity
to continue or exit the sales
process in other words forcing people to
make a decision
to opt in or opt out right but not
leaving it
up to guesswork that's the big
difference here
and again the do becomes just connecting
the executive buyer uh with you or your
founder and ceo
uh to um to close the business
you're never going to be able to do this
in sales
until you get comfortable and get good
at
getting beyond the one-on-one
conversation with people
too often i see sales people having a
one-on-one conversation
and moving it forward in the sales
funnel without widening the conversation
and i would argue
that uh even a well-qualified
opportunity
is not qualified anymore uh if
the contact in the account is not
willing to widen the conversation
so what does that mean it means
connecting people with your team
with people on their team you do that by
making us a simple request a simple
statement
listen our standard practice is to
confirm
the fit with the right people in your
organization
you know who do you recommend we connect
with you know our team with
and how do you and i work together to
coordinate that
right you're not asking people for
permission here
right um you're you're asking people
how do you go about doing this not
whether doing this is a good idea
right most sales people really struggle
with how to expand the conversation
within an organization
offer you know and to help move this
along offer to bring your experts to the
table
and they might in turn bring one of
their more technical colleagues
or if you're not the ceo often to bring
your ceo or founder into the
conversation
which will encourage them to bring in
their boss
now if the opportunity is truly
qualified
they should not only be agreeable they
should be enthusiastic
about engaging others uh in their
organization
in the conversation right because the
sales decisions are made by teams
not individuals right so you want to
start pulling in the decision-making
unit
you want to start forming that if
however your contact is
resistant or circumspect about
involving other people they're not
qualified you're not talking to the
right person
uh or they've got an alternative agenda
right something's wrong here right um
when people start introducing you to
other people on their team
that means they're willing to expend
some of their political capital inside
their organization
the reverse is also true somebody's not
willing to take any
risk uh they've got another agenda in
mind
or you're talking to the wrong person or
something else is wrong you need to find
out
but it's not a qualified opportunity
once the conversations expanded beyond
your initial contact it becomes much
easier for you to reach out
with each person in your organization
independently
never ever reach over somebody's head
without permission
right i was i was talking with the
founder and this must have been 10 years
ago but i remember
like it was yesterday and he thought he
was being so smart
that he learned their email construct
from one of their engineers and he went
to their management page
and just started um ambushing their
management team
by applying their name to their email
construct
right over the head of the person he was
talking with
and guess where that went well nowhere
very fast never ever reach over
somebody's head without their permission
just request an email introduction and
always cc
uh people that you're in discussions
with as a courtesy in sales
get beyond the one-on-one conversation i
can't emphasize how important this is
always attempt to connect people on your
team
with people on their team the more
people
that on the prospects team that you
engage with people
on your team the higher the probability
of winning a new
paying customer that's a fact that's a
sales fact
so get in the habit of getting
comfortable
and developing methods to get beyond
the one-on-one conversation
remember with every interaction you have
with the prospective customer have a
plan in place to help them and add value
and every time you give something to a
prospect
ask for something in return it's a soft
ask
what you're doing is you're getting
people in the habit of making these
trades
this is not just a one-way street you've
got to break
people of the traditional buyer gets
everything they want
you know there's the old golden rule
in sales for buyers and that is whoever
has the gold makes the rules
right forget about that right get people
into a collegial relationship where they
generally
are interested in helping you help them
and they do that by sharing insights
and interpret the timing and the quality
of their response
as a primary indicator of whether
they're qualified
to take your time
it turns out that prospective customers
who hang in
with your process you're in a good
position and you've earned the right to
ask for their business
okay now i want to talk a little bit
more about qualifying and disqualifying
and we've only got a few minutes left so
i want to cover this material here
i think i started our session on tuesday
by sharing with you my philosophy
about sales being that it's um it's it's
the opposite of what you read in a book
where the books tell you it's all
about qualifying customers and
in my in my experience qualified
buyers are easy to spot it's it's
uncovering the
ones that appear to be qualified that
are not that are waste of your time
that you really have to get good at so i
believe that sales is not about
qualifying prospective customers and let
me explain to you why
let's pretend that over here on the left
here
uh these are the the the uh lee
the the prospects that 10 percent
that surfaced from those 500 leads those
suspects
right 90 of them were
not qualified where you've got this 10
percent
being qualified as prospects
let's unpack that 10
well that consists of on either end a
yes or a no
and in between a yes but a no but
or an unknown most of them are unknown
you just
don't know right um it's
the exception but sometimes it happens
that you get to a yes
or no quickly but oftentimes when you're
developing opportunities
it merges into uh
you know moving more toward a yes with a
butt or concerns
or more toward a no with a butt with
concerns right
uncontested yeses and no those are easy
right they go to contract or they exit
your process
you get a yes but sometimes it's
possible to negotiate
to a yes by making a concession and even
a no but
sometimes it's possible to convert to a
yes
but it's not a concession it's a huge
contortion
usually it's this middle ground here
that is often a huge waste of time
for sales people and where you have to
get really really good
at flushing people out of this what i
call
the slow no zone right it's
it's a no it's just a slow no and it's
taking up your time
your valuable time in sales you want to
spend your time
up here not down here
so you've basically got two options you
can
work 18 hour days right flushing those
slow nose out and of course you'll need
a therapist
or you can get good at proactively
disqualifying
prospects and that's what i want to talk
to you about next is
how do you get good at proactively
disqualifying prospects
so sales is not about qualifying
prospective customers
it's about disqualifying prospects with
the appearance of real
that'll waste your time
so organizations tend to buy when the
following conditions exist
there's recognition of an unsolved
problem or need that's a top priority
for the organization
where the pain cost and risk is clear
and quantifiable
and a well-respected advocate inside
that organization owns the initiative
when these conditions exist this
organization is going to buy
from somebody and there is a budget
available
when you combine combine these
conditions with the perception
that you're offering is the best
alternative and they have confidence in
your team and company and a trusted
relationship with the sales rep
then the budgets available for you and
there's
lots of proxies for know when just one
of these up criteria
is not firmly established
it turns out that sales people uh you'll
learn
through your career that people that you
work with
have 25 different ways of saying no
when i cover sales people in my
in my normal curriculum which we skipped
here one of the
myths with salespeople is that
sales people are liars they'll tell you
anything you want to get a deal
and um the lesson that i've learned
there is sales people are not liars
buyers are the liars they're the people
that will
um misdirect uh misguide
lie whatever for their own um agendas
and ambitions
it's the buyers that are far less
forthright with people than sales people
so you know you're on the phone with
somebody for example
you know i'm not sure you ask people
you're trying to expand the conversation
i'm not sure who the right person is for
you to speak with you know you get
something
like that from the from somebody on the
phone interpret them
as saying how about no one right this
person's not qualified
or somebody starts a response to a
question
with the word management has decided to
blah blah blah
whenever anyone starts a sentence with
the word management
guess what that means it means one
they're not management and they probably
have no idea
what management's even thinking you're
not talking to the right person
um i'm sure none of you have heard this
one before
it's not in this year's budget when
people tell you that
it's just a low priority it's a proxy
for low priority
um i don't know if you've heard this
too often this is a pretty common reply
we would like to partner with you um
that's a proxy for
uh i don't have any access to money
or um somebody starts out you've had a
conversation going with somebody maybe
it's your third or fourth meeting
and just out of the blue an unsolicited
compliment comes out of your contact
i really love you know we really
like this we love you guys right it just
um you know uh
you just wait for the butt here right
what this person
um is doing is um
overcompensating right um they're
deciding to go in another direction
or for whatever reason they're not going
to be moving forward with you
uh this person won't buy from you but
they want you to like them
right so they they're going to give you
a compliment
um you know to offset the bad news here
all right so whenever you get a
completely
unsolicited compliment in sales you know
you pretty much
know you're screwed uh so that's another
sort of telltale sign uh or
a different proxy for no so these are
just examples and i
lay these out there just as examples i
don't expect you to remember them
as a matter of fact i don't even expect
you to
apply these because they're very very
difficult
to discern so i'm going to give you some
techniques here
that make these much more obvious and
actionable
by the way the most common proxy for no
in sales
is getting ghosted right people are just
rude and they just will not follow up
so in sales no is your always
your second best answer and the slow no
is always your worst answer
so in sales if you do not take ownership
of the word
no prepare to spend most of your time
working deals that go nowhere
so no is elusive right buying signals
easy to spot stalling signals often
ambiguous
the vast majority of your sales efforts
should result
in no thank you especially early in your
sales process
but for alternative agendas they do not
right and the reason is it doesn't come
easily for most people
right they want to avoid conflict right
or they've been talking
with you a while and they have to move
away and they're a little embarrassed
right because they are going to take a
change in direction
or they've been taught at a very young
age that it's not
actually encouraged to say no
or maybe it's just the rude buyer
attitude or
more commonly in my experience it's an
ulterior motive
right you're training them for free
you're
um giving them knowledge they need to
build something with somebody else or
internally
or you just got somebody that's looking
to
upskill themselves and learn because
they happen to have time in their
schedule
so it's the prospects themselves that
will
will misdirect lie delay ghost when they
turn you down
and they're going to make up any reason
and unfortunately a simple no is rarely
one of them
now i've had the privilege of presenting
um
my uh my my sales training and my
lectures
in 26 countries over the past um 10
years
and i can tell you that the saying no
problem
it transcends gender national and ethnic
borders
it's everywhere right it's not just
um exclusive to the us
culture and two years ago in my travels
i think i finally discovered the origin
of the saying no problem does anyone
want to guess
on chat what country is the source of
the saying no problem
this should be fun anyone have any ideas
what country is the source
of the saying no problem india nope
uk nope china can of bingo
curry you nailed it canada exactly no
japan is not
japan has the yes problem yes means no
in canada they're just too nice right
um they're the nicest people on the
planet you ever want to meet and they
will never ever
say no so i believe that that is the
origin
of the saying no problem um i presented
this to
um a hundred founders up in halifax
three years ago uh no it wasn't three
years ago was
maybe a year and a half ago and um
i heard with them that i i thought that
they were the source of the saying no
problem and
somebody in the crowd raised their hand
and i called him and they said
i'm sorry i apologize for that
which just goes to show you how nice
they are
so um understand that
the no is always going to be elusive
here right and one of the biggest
challenges in sales is
uncovering the slow no graciously
and efficiently so you can invest your
time more productively elsewhere
right so most of our most of us are not
clairvoyant you're not going to pick up
on those super subtle signals
right because it's not those are not
easy to discern
so i'll give you a couple of suggestions
here one
early on the sales process ask for no
just ask for it say listen i'm just
gonna take up three minutes of your time
i think we can really help you guys
based upon what my understanding is
about
your company and your needs uh give me
two minutes of your time
and please say no at the end if you
don't think it's a good fit
or whatever just please say no ask for
it and what you're gonna find when you
give
people permission to say no they'll go
ahead and say it
unless they're being real evil in their
attention
where if they don't say no they're
either qualified to move forward
or they're being quite evil in their
intention
in wasting your time so early on
while you're qualifying prospects ask
for no
later on in your sales process what you
do is you say
no for people right i call this
off-ramping
right and what off-ramping does it's a
way of purging
slow-nose from your sales funnel in a
clear and elegant way to provoke
buying installing signals so off-ramping
is a sales technique for purging slo-nos
from your pipeline by proactively
offering prospects the ability to opt in
or
opt out of your sales process i.e take
the off-ramp
this is the primary skill of the
sales facilitator what are off ramps
they're non-threatening questions tests
or challenges that provide
insight into things that you need to
know about the account
what are their priorities what are they
predisposed to
how are they going to return on their
investment here what's the size of the
impact
right what are they objecting to who are
you
up against what is their decision making
process
you can discover a lot of this
information
by uh in off-ramping ways
that if they don't give you the right
answer you know that they're not
qualified
to take up your time so off ramps are
thoughtful probing questions that
provoke
clear buying installing signals that are
observable
and actionable by you and they help
prospects either
self-qualify or disengage so i'll give
you a couple of examples here
um you know you have trouble getting a
hold of somebody you finally get them on
the phone
uh you say listen tom um
i've had trouble you know we seem to
slow things down last couple months
sounds like you got a lot in your plate
right now
maybe we should just pick up our
discussion in a month or two
that's a very considerate thing to offer
somebody in sales
right and the off ramp here might be hey
you know what
you're probably right thank you very
much let's touch base in a couple of
months
to the contrary the buying signal is hey
no way we're dying here sorry i've been
um i've been um you know heads down
um on closing the quarter business here
i apologize
for not uh staying in touch with you but
we really need to pick up our
conversation and move it forward
here
i often like to preempt people in their
alternatives
so um i ask people early in the sales
process
or as we start to get into it have you
considered x or y
or x or y are competitors or
alternatives to me
and what does that do when you do that
well one
is um when you do that you get some real
good insights
on how far people are along in their
sales process
but also implied here by asking this
is your confidence in outperforming
x and y so the off-ramp response
to that question is those options hadn't
occurred to us
well um you know that if they are
serious about buying
um they would have considered those
options as part of their due diligence
so either they're not qualified or
they're very very early
in the sales process conversely the
buying signal here is
you know absolutely they're both
non-starters
here's why and now you get to really
understand how you
stack up and why they're what your what
your differentiated
value is when you're trying to
understand a little bit more about
the the impact and the cost and the roi
you can tell somebody you really
understand their pain but what's the
real cost behind this
right now if they haven't measured the
financial impact of that
um it's either a stalling or an off ramp
here
because people are going to buy
something they're going to want to kind
of justify it
um you know in dollars and cents right
uh conversely
they can say listen we understand this
pain it's costing our company
approximately x dollars every year right
that's a clear uh buying signal
right by asking a simple open-ended
non-threatening question you want to you
want to figure out
whether your solution uh um the size of
the problem you're solving
um is compatible with your pricing
you just ask people you know how many
people in your team are impacted
right they could say well we just
started to focus on this
issue or you know what everyone in the
company knows this is a real problem
lastly i'll give you one last example
you get off a phone call
uh with somebody maybe on you know
the west coast somebody's senior
management it was a brutal phone call
um the senior manager uh had a very
antagonistic
uh attitude toward your company and your
your offering
uh the call didn't go well so you call
up
your your uh ally in the organization
your champion
uh you just geez you know what he
certainly took a different view
um what do you have any suggestions well
you know what uh unfortunately he rarely
changes his mind
or the buying signal well the reason he
was like that is he got burned on this
before and i've got some thoughts on
how we can get him on board lastly if
you're selling people efficiency
try to understand um whether
the uh you're selling efficiency to the
person
whose product you're uh you displace
right that's a very important thing in
terms of understanding what level of
organization you sell into
you know you can ask them a simple
open-ended question isn't management
just going to tell
your team to suck it up right you're
you're turning the crank
350 times a day isn't that your job
well it's a distinct possibility or you
know what
management already told us and
recognizes there's much more
there's much smarter things we can be
doing with our time and they
we have their full support on this
so sales off ramping when people have
the appearance of being qualified but
they're really not
what it does is it provides a fast
frictionless
exit from your sales process
on the contrary when you offer uh
somebody who is genuinely qualified and
off-ramp
what it does is it serves to strengthen
their resolve
it earns their trust and it provides you
valuable insights in how to win the
business the best measure of effective
off-ramping
is um when a well-qualified prospect
takes an off-ramp and resurfaces 18
months later
i'd like to tell you a quick story about
this in anecdote but i don't have time
i just want to close with a couple of
different
points i want to make here because we're
running short on time
so offering prospects off-ramps what it
does is it builds
confidence and trust in you by not
driving to a yes you're not coming off
as a salesperson
you're offering people you're asking
people probing
logical questions that determine fit
and help people in their own mind um
opt in or opt out of your process and
you're not coming across
as a salesperson but you're building
trust by asking questions
that confirm that you have their best
interest in mind
it turns out that people who have sold
themselves
with your assistance of course become
much stronger advocates
of a purchasing decision so effective
enterprise sales is not measured by the
statements
or claims that you make but by the
thoughtful probing questions you ask
your willingness and your confidence
to enable people to opt in or opt out of
your process
of course your competence here your
competencies your special insights and
knowledge to solve their needs
and how you help them overcome
legitimate concerns
and objections remember
um i mentioned early day one that the
mid
mit definition of early stage sales
sales
is debugging people's objections to
spending money
well that's what it is until the only
objection that remains
is price if people object over price
congratulations you're probably getting
close to a deal
it's not often that people object over
price unless all there are
other objections have been satisfied
so over the past couple days um i've
covered
what you probably consider to be a lot
of material
there's a lot more i just outlined here
some of the things that i've covered i
picked that i thought might be uh
helpful
for you um here there's lots more to be
learned in sales i'm still learning
um i offer uh training and coaching
to organizations
both on premise and in
zoom formats here one day
to one week formats both for for
startups and scale-ups
and two years ago started offering
remote
sales coaching sessions to founders
and their go-to-market teams via zoom
through uh monthly pre-scheduled
90-minute sessions
i'm always busy but hey i'm always
interested in learning
about new opportunities with programs or
companies
if you're aware of an organization
or company that can benefit from my work
please reach out to me to discuss
very much appreciate it it's my hope
that
over the past couple of sessions you've
um
you've learned one or two things that um
help you improve sales performance uh
and accelerate growth of your company
happy hunting
i've got a couple minutes here maybe
five minutes for some q a if anyone has
any
questions thank you so much ken that was
really amazing
uh so so much knowledge and it was like
um
very practical very very insightful so
i'm sure a lot of us will be reaching
out to you
uh individually uh in the last uh just
four minutes we have with you here
there's a couple questions in the chat
maybe the first one from john stock
the best techniques or tips for cold
email call or linkedin messages
for code outreach yeah um i'll hearken
back to the
to the arkham's razor principle right
um be brief right
um i can tell you this i get bombed
all the time in um linkedin
in email and anything beyond two
sentences
i won't even read it i don't have the
time it's not qualified to take my time
but if you can get somebody's attention
right
in a sentence and just say you know
click here to connect
or let me know if you want to connect
right be kind of informal
but be very very brief i find those to
be much more impactful versus people
that'll write
really three or four paragraphs i mean
you really expect people to read
three or four paragraphs in a in a in
mail and linkedin or email
probably not so um
i would encourage you to to also uh talk
with
marketing experts direct marketing
experts they have a great deal of
expertise on this but
that's my own tunes that presents on
that topic
great and brian uh wasn't on the session
on tuesday he's asking if there's any
couple sales tools or
resources that you could recommend is
there a podcast that you listen to or
some resource
you know i'm the worst guy uh to ask
that question because you know what
i don't i don't watch podcasts and i
don't read sales books
i don't do any of that uh stuff i learn
through my own mistakes and mostly
uh and just working with companies in
practice
um i wish i could point you
in a couple of resources um actually
coincidentally one of the
books that i read
uh recently uh that i thought was really
insightful here so
um it's a book called mindset and um
what what carol dweck does really
is reinforce the value of storytelling
in sales
um anecdotes and storytelling
it turns out that people make buying
decisions more based on
emotion and instinct and they justify it
with logic
so if you start with roi and expect
people to make a purchasing decision
you're going at it backwards right so
start by appealing to people's emotions
and
instinct and the best way you do that is
you
tell show stories and what carol does is
give you a really nice
outline for stories here and turn in
and rules of thumb in terms of relevance
and brevity
and all those kinds of things to be able
to build sort of a repertoire of stories
that you could share with people because
at the end of the day
sales comes down to um you know everyone
has the same question in sales
and that is have you solved a similar
problem for somebody just like me and
when can we talk with them
right and you don't want to share those
references with people right away
so what you have to do is be able to
share those stories with people
either anecdotally or through case
studies and get really good at that and
this book is
i think provides some really valuable
insights into that so hopefully that
that's helpful
great thank you so much ken and if
anyone wants to reach you for the
consulting linkedin is the best way
uh to comment yeah linkedin uh you know
uh
you i i gave you my uh email address
there i believe
uh let me yeah it's it's on your um
on your yep that's my email address you
can uh connect with me any way you want
uh joe regina thank you very much for
inviting me
i really appreciate the opportunity um
and um happy hunting everybody